this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software James welcome to our Triple E
software an se radio thank you thank you
for introducing yourselves to the
listeners well my name is Susanne
Robertson and I'm a principal of the
Atlantic Systems guild it's a an
organization that's been in existence
for how long James 27 years I think now
and there are six office in it and one
of my partners in fact is James who's
sitting next to me as you've no doubt
gathered I'm also a principal of the
Atlantic Systems guilt if we can portray
some of that as we go through the
interview excellent well what we want to
talk today is a looking at the
intersection between agile which has
been around now well over a decade and
its intersection with requirements so I
thought I'd start asking about when in
your requirements work both of you
became familiar or aware of agile
projects and its potential impact on
requirements work was about actually
about 10 years ago wasn't it when Kent
Beck wrote the book about extreme
programming I think it was a little
earlier than that but at least I think
Kent Beck wrote the book a little
earlier than that but without checking
let's say ten years okay well I think
probably it came into the mainstream you
know people he wrote very well he had
some very good ideas and it captured a
lot of people's attention and they said
oh great
this means that we can just work in a
small group and we can just build things
actually one of the big mistakes I think
that people made not that Becky really
intended them to do this but one of the
big mistakes that people made was to say
well if we work closely with another
person we don't really need to do any
requirements work because we were there
and we can build software very software
everyone focused
and those are my earliest memories of it
what about you I think my earliest
memories are were reading an extreme
programming but also the animal use word
hysteria but the extreme zealotry that
surrounded the introduction of agile
techniques but this has been very much a
facet of software engineering that as
soon as some new paradigm comes along
everybody not everybody but a lot of
people leap onto the bandwagon and throw
everything away we don't do what
scientists do which is stand on the
shoulders of giants as an industry we
tend to throw everything away and start
again and this happens as Suzanne and I
have seen it happen four or five times
and our working lifetime
the problem with agile and I'm talking
here about be a heir child following a
method whether it's XP or scrum or
crystal or many one of the other flavors
of it is that the baby got thrown out
with the bathwater
the problem was seen as requirements
were all wrong there we have to have
this giant requirement document that had
to be written and complete and then
thrown over the transom to the
development team and this was taking a
long time for anything to happen and
requirements were pointed out as being
the villain of the piece and so the
early Angeles threw out requirements and
I think that was a huge mistake I think
we're going to come back to that in a
you know and being
later on so my early you know if you're
asking my early you know responses to
Angela was that this is living
dangerously because we've gotten rid of
something that's very valuable whereas
really there's room for two things here
I think that would be my but did you
find that your clients were expressing
that view or were they taking a more
pragmatic middle road which they started
to move to our job well the clients were
either confused and following some kind
of a step-by-step method or being driven
by sometimes by managers who had very
little knowledge about what agile was
about it was just if you're agile that
means that you can get things done much
more quickly and consequently a lot of
the teams that I was working with and
have been working with just get an awful
lot of pressure to be a German and
really that translate to get this done
more quickly and I think the more
intelligent views a lot more intelligent
approaches have been when people have
said well hang on what does it actually
mean and why is it a good idea because
it is a good idea it's a terrific idea
so what what is it and you then you know
you make the obstruction and you think
well what it really is is you want to
produce value but and you want to
produce it because we build systems for
people and systems I'm talking about
them in the wide you know not just
software but systems and we want to be
able to produce this value and we want
to be able to do it quickly and we want
to be able to turn on a sixpence when
business has changed and they've change
more and more often and I think the
people who really understand what agile
is all about understand that they don't
say being agile means you do scrum not
being agile means you don't do
requirements or whatever it is that they
pick up from the patchwork quilt so it's
understanding the motivation the
rationale for a job
than the mechanics of it absolutely I
think that's you know my point about big
a agile and little a agile we're very
much in favor of little a agile I think
if you follow a two slavishly a method
it can lead you down the wrong road no
matter what the what the method is and
that was my experience with the clients
who are early adopters are but they felt
that if they simply did everything that
the method began a jille method said to
do that their problems would be over
well it turns out that doesn't work it
doesn't work that way we can't do we
can't work following a Swedish method
but if we're flexible and not rigid
in other words little a agile then it
doesn't really fit well if people
understand what little a agile is then
they can pick the techniques that suit
particular situations like if they say
ok what we're really trying to do is to
understand the problem well enough as
quickly as we can to decide what to do
that will give people the most value
sometimes that will mean using a
particular technique or building a
particular type of model sometimes it'll
mean going through different sorts of
cycles using prototypes using
simulations or all the things that we
know about as being useful techniques
and approaches but the problem is that
because it was new and because it was
presented as a technique or an approach
that's how people got to know about it
so they thought about it as a technique
rather than as what's behind it and
that's what we were we took that that's
what we were meaning by my little a
agile yes most of my clients now are
moving away from Big Ang are the little
HR when they're getting more value
of bitter thinking as opposed to how
this little a agile manifest itself in
projects today by the adoption of things
outside of the original big a agile camp
for example something that is near and
dear to our hearts is systemic thinking
yeah this is not mentioned in most of
the textbooks but it's a very important
part of what we do
innovation for example is not mentioned
anywhere that I've been able to find but
nevertheless is absolutely vital if
we're going to be building useful things
and I think the I don't know who first
said this but and to paraphrase it you
can build something any way you want you
to build software any way you want
but if it doesn't do something useful in
by definition it's absolutely useless
and something that in the early adoption
of agile the emphasis was on doing
things quickly well I'm also going to
say you can build something as quickly
as you want to but if it doesn't do
what's needed to be done it's absolutely
useless and so I think clients or
customers and software builders are now
coming to the realization that it's
better to take a little bit longer to do
something and get it right as opposed to
build something totally useless on-time
on-budget
no but I think another thing that you
see when people are really coming to
grips with with literally agile is that
they're not driven by any rigid process
not at all what they're looking for is
to come to grips with the problem as
quickly as they can so that they can
make some decisions about which bits to
do what with which bits to go further in
and they might it might be a team who
work in a particular way that they like
or they might be experimenting with
something something else but it's it's
not driven by any process or you know
any any rigid person I think one of the
you often hear about agile is that
either the stakeholders really can't
express their requirements or whether by
the time they've been able to be
expressed them the requirements have
changed we're living in a such a dynamic
world that it's almost pointless to
document the requirements in any way
that we might consider traditional
what's your view on that
I think requirements change much more
slowly than people say they do the
problem is that the requirements are
never gathered correctly in the first
instance and so when they are presented
back to the users the users are saying
no that's not what we meant and that's
taken to be a changing requirement well
it's not a changing requirement the
basic business need is still there it
just hasn't been expressed properly one
of the things that I noticed about early
Begay agile adoption was the emphasis
was on building something let's go and
build some software and even this macho
stuff about having iteration times time
than hours if not minutes in order to
keep on producing software keep on
producing girls keep on producing stuff
this is producing a solution okay but
it's not necessarily a solution to the
right problem just because we deliver up
a piece of software does not mean you're
delivering value and this almost
chanting of a mantra that went on about
constant delivery of customer value
software is not necessarily valuable if
it doesn't do what's needed then it's
useless it is not valuable at all and so
I'm seeing more and more now the
stepping back from that constant
delivery of software into getting a
better understanding of what the real
problem is and I
that's extremely healthy well also the
other thing that you you mentioned the D
word documentation I think there's a lot
of misunderstanding about that as well I
think that people think about if you do
requirements it means you've got to
produce a lot of formally written
documentation in large documents bla bla
bla but it's not that at all what it is
is you want to leave a trail and if
you're working in a co-located
environment there's nothing to stop you
leaving your trail on the walls or in a
non-slip Church we've got we've got
video cameras we've got some
cameras all over the place everybody's
got them we've got all sorts of
technology that we can use to free us
from having to sit down and say well now
it's time to do the documentation I mean
you should only do a translation into
another form if you need to do that
translation in order for whoever it is
you're trying to communicate with to
understand it so if you're outsourcing
or something like that you probably need
to spend more of your budget on
translation but you shouldn't do it if
you don't need to so the reported demise
of more traditional requirements
techniques is premature I don't know
because I'm wondering what you mean by
more traditional requirements techniques
documenting requirements in a way that
makes them immeasurable if you have got
a specification that can be analyzed for
various properties completeness and
correctness but I think you see that you
could do that in a co-located team with
white walls I mean I know that's extreme
but you can do it the key thing and this
is a big key is to tell the difference
between the form and the content and the
content is what you're trying to
communicate now if you've got a team for
example and they are talking to each
other about requirements
let's say and they say well we've got
125 requirements if they haven't got a
shared mental model of what a
requirement is they're just going to
lose the mean so you've got to have some
kind of shared mental model and it
doesn't have to be imposed by anybody
else as long as that team understands
that if you've got that then you can
trace the requirements you can make them
measurable you can say whether whether
you've got this beautiful requirement
when you've got a rationale whether you
haven't but it just might be in a
different form so agile brings us new
forms of requirement the quality remains
but the form at ages absolutely I think
that requirements now we're accepting
that some requirements can be verbally
communicated that they can be sketched
and scribbled on the back of story cards
and so forth so there's nothing wrong
with that at all I think it comes back
copy - what are you calling a
requirement and when you say traditional
requirements if you think about
traditional requirements of being a
business analyst goes talks to the
customers writes down whatever they say
translates that into some form and gives
it developers yeah that's been gone for
quite some time if you talk about
requirements in terms of let me call
there's little higher requirements in
terms of actually filing out what the
real problem is and having some way of
communicating that and it doesn't matter
whether it's written or not then that's
the way we see requirements going today
there are some needs for you mentioned
documentation a moment ago there is a
need for documentation still what we
have learned from the agile methods that
documenting what a piece of software
does is completely useless because the
code is the Best Documentary
functionality however it's not important
to document that
simply because we can read the code if I
know what it's doing documenting why
something exists is very important
because in five years time when the
software still lives and let's face it
software is living longer and longer and
longer I sometimes do a brief survey in
my requirements courses and find that
there is software belonging to
organizations represented in the room
that is older than the students
represented in the room so knowing why
something exists is important so that
kind of documentation has not gone away
or at least the companies that were
developing software without keeping that
kind of documentation to realize they do
need it after all the rationale behind
something which is why we have it on our
snow cards to always document the reason
behind something and I think it comes
back to when you talk about requirements
or we've talked earlier about
requirements changing if you do discover
the rationale for a requirement or even
the rationale for a use case of the
rationale for a whole piece of work you
find that that concentrates everybody's
mind on exactly what the problem is
and you find the problem doesn't change
but proposed solutions to that problem
do change and so rather than demise I'm
going to say no requirements work is
morphing into something different with
an emphasis on rationale reasoning
behind things with an emphasis on
discovering the real work as opposed to
the emphasis being on traditionally
writing the DeLarge
I do having said all that there is still
a need for the larger document if you're
outsourcing and let's face it most
organizations today are outsourcing you
need to write the complete specification
because when you send that off to India
or Russia or Indonesia or wherever
you're sending it to they do need a
complete specification very few
outsources are going to work eat rudely
with you I can see how that can work for
functionality functional requirements
what about quality requirement usability
reliability
I've seen them scribbled on the backs of
it and use the story cards and so on do
you think those have to be documented in
different ways in agile I do yes because
the qualitative requirements what we
call the non-functional requirements
quite often exist across several
business event to use cases across the
number of different transactions what
have you aim partitioning you want to
use so attaching them to one story card
is possibly not the best thing to do
simply because if there's another
similar story they may not pick up the
same non-functional requirement so it's
almost as if the qualitative
requirements have to be separately
documented because they are an
overarching quality of the whole
development effort as opposed to one in
particular yes but they also need to be
connected to the relevant bits of
functionality and they also need to be
connected to the people who really
understand that particular type of
non-functional requirement so it's like
now you've got the thread that goes from
the functionalities are non-functional
requirements to the particular
stakeholders who are the experts and
we're seeing this more and more that
because our systems can do many more
things and can support many more
non-functional requirements we're seeing
more and more like internal consulting
stakeholders people who are usability
experts who just focus on those on that
type of requirement and they're experts
in them and if there is some kind of
formal way of from writing those things
down or making them available to people
in
that means that you then start to open
the door to reuse to really to open the
door to reuse because you don't have to
go and discover those usability
requirements and write their
measurements down every single time but
that doesn't happen unless you actually
build up that sociology in the
organization so taking agile with the
small a how do you think your consulting
and requirements practices have changed
over the last decade how if you modified
Valere or changed what you teach or
train people well now because people are
becoming more aware of a wider picture
not enough but they are becoming they're
starting to realize that we have to be
system thinkers because of that we can
actually get them to start thinking
about the requirements and really at the
beginning of doing a piece of work and I
really mean at the beginning before you
actually start to say okay let's go and
find out all the atomic requirements why
not identify just just that really
simple model that we that we've used the
scope stakeholders and the goals if you
can make that visible as the highest
level requirements but you're actually
making the measurable and at that point
identify the pieces well enough to start
prioritizing and this is where the the a
that the little egg comes in because it
earlier you can start prioritizing the
pieces the the more agile you're able to
be because you can say oh look you know
we done this this quick analysis we can
identify the pieces and we've got 50
pieces and we're going to go through a
quick prioritization whereabouts of the
major value where are the difficulties
you know risks Causton but you can do
this quite quickly with this beyond
sketched requirements requirements that
are not perfectly formed as we well I
expect them to be introduced connected
back
to the functional side of it's connected
back to the scope the non-functional
side is connected back to the
stakeholders so even though you don't
know everything
downwards in the detail you do know what
you're talking about at my high level in
other words high level doesn't mean I
don't really know what I'm talking about
maybe I'll find out high level means we
understand this we understand what we
think it is now so that we will know if
it changes and then that means you can
then you can be very young job Sarah
Kevin can work on this piece and we're
going to deliver something or we're
going to work on this piece because we
think it's the riskiest thing and if we
can't do this we we may as well stop
doing the project it's those things that
people can mean the canoes to be much
more agile I think the changes I've seen
is that the big edge our folks are
coming much more around to looking very
much at the problem space and this is
where if you want to talk about
traditional requirements and traditional
agile come together it's an
investigation of the problem space to
find out what is it we're really trying
to do here and what we're trying to do
is not to build a piece of software what
we're trying to do is improve a business
and there's a subtle very important and
very important difference between them
between the two of them the other one is
as to then mentioned prioritization of
looking in the problem space cutting it
up any way you like but carving it up
into pieces and then prioritizing the
pieces because a lot of what we do is
not important but a lot of what is being
done is not important we built software
to carry out functionality that's only
used once every five years or isn't that
important doesn't happen very often adds
very little value to the owner
the software it's a prioritization I
think is causing people to think about
much more closely about what they're
doing and not develop as much software
but only developed for the important the
important things you know how little can
we actually get away with it
you've mentioned systemic thinking to me
systemic thinking involves some kind of
modeling or walking through something
but it involves artifacts and those
sorts of models and artifacts aren't
typically things you've associated with
big a agile they they tend to eschew
that kind of modeling and they see it as
documentation do you use those sorts of
techniques at all in your approaches oh
absolutely not
absolutely systemic thinking is is
hugely important because it doesn't
matter what your method is saying you
can't build a diagram is rubbish simply
because a systemic thinking is difficult
enough if you're trying to do it all
inside your head or on the back of a
card it's not going to work okay
typically you do need some kind of model
just to see the effect of what you're
doing and building a piece of software
so let me just back up a moment here
talking just a little while ago about
the problem space investigating the
problem space this is something we're
seeing more and more people thinking
about the work area that they're trying
to improve and not just a software okay
the early big a agile went straight into
a piece of software I have no idea
really whether it would solve the right
problem because they're just looking at
this very narrow focus well focus is
broadening we're looking at a piece of
work but then systemic thinking says you
would look at that piece of work if we
change that piece of work what happens
to the rest of the organization that
it's going into if it's a simple
simplistic piece of software like a game
for example you don't care
what happens around that because the
person is going to buy the game or not
what else they do in their life you're
not concerned with if you go and put in
a new inventory control system into a
car manufacturer you're very concerned
about what effect that has on
manufacturing on finance on personnel on
everything else and if we don't think
about all these other things then we've
got the potential for catastrophe but
that points to something that I've seen
people are more and more ready now to go
back to things that have proved to be
useful in the past and connect them to
this idea of being iterative being agile
being being able to look at things in
hierarchies just as you know good
systems thinkers can do so for example
people are now saying well process
models work in certain cases down models
work state models work systems flow
dynamics models work but they were also
starting to understand how you can
connect those so that you're being
consistent and you can you can choose
which ones to use in what situations but
you can connect them into the overall
picture of the project that you're doing
and that that harks back to something I
said earlier where people can choose the
techniques the procedures the
visualizations that are most appropriate
to to what they're doing but they does
rely on a really important thing about
Cisco Systems thinking skill which is I
mentioned earlier being able to
distinguish between what is there
because of the form and what's there
because of the content not the forms bad
but just to be able to understand which
is which so do you see your role in part
nowadays as helping a project choose the
right techniques and tools to use
little big pick-and-mix agile shop
there's a lot of choice out there you
may be overwhelmed by the choice is that
a role that you see as we do we do that
quite a bit with people and you know
help that obviously you've got to learn
a little bit about that you know that
first high level analysis and then from
there because we've seen so many
different approaches use we can save
people why don't you start with I don't
know a data model for example because
this is a very data heavy problem and
you're going to get much more insight
more quickly if you start with data well
these people might never have done that
before because they were used to
starting with worrying about processes
or functions or whatever they were used
to start so it's trying to help people
to free themselves from this is the way
we always do it also three teams from
believing that the model or the
technique is the purpose but the purpose
is to do some work to improve the owners
business in some way getting into Wars
about techniques or diagrams and so
forth a lot of what I found myself doing
is is saying to people you can build a
model of data any way you like and if
three different people are using three
notations that's fine because
essentially they're all talking about
the same thing
and there's no one model that's going to
be notably superior to to another in
fact you can actually do it in a tabular
form if you want to it really matter but
getting people to realize that it's hard
if they haven't had a lot of experience
because it does rely on on having done a
fair amount of project work so that you
can understand these different
abstractions we we've been focusing a
lot on helping people to become better
abstractors
because I think everybody can be better
at abstraction it's just that quite
often you're not talk that way you're
talking you know a particular way to do
it rather than what's what's behind it
and even if you were taught you need a
little bit more experience before you
can say ah this is really the same as
this or this this will work better now
so we've been developing some models I
mean our Brown cowl model is is very
useful as a way of helping people to see
you can you can make it you know there
were four different viewpoints that you
can take of anything that are you spit
useful and traditionally in business
analysis they said as is and to be well
that's not really enough you need the as
is how it's done and the two billion how
it'll be but you also need what's behind
it and that's really looking at the the
purpose and the essence and all of that
so it's models and things like that
that we've helped people to you said as
a starting point to help them to be more
agile because if you know that you can
take four different useful viewpoint you
take a lots more but more useful ones
then it doesn't matter where you start
and that's what we that's what makes
people that if some instruction is one
of those incredibly useful abilities to
be able to see something independently
of its implementation in other words the
underlying reason behind it we often
refer to this as the essence of the
problem and once you can see the essence
see the reason behind something
it does help enormous Lee to come up
with better implementations my earlier
criticism of big a agile rushing into an
implementation was that they were not
looking at the underlying problem other
words when not taking any abstractions
at all and simply producing piece of
software to complain about changing
requirements is by not looking at the
abstraction you build a piece of
software it's probably not going to meet
the real need and so when a change is
asked for that piece of
yeah that's taken to be a change in
requirement well it not at all the
original requirement is the same and if
people take a little bit of time to
abstract away from implementations and
you can get to see the real the real
problem I think that helps enormous Lee
but you see if you if you're really
agile supposing that you're trying to
understand a requirement and you you're
having trouble and people having trouble
telling you all you you just don't get
it then it's an intelligent thing to do
to build some kind of simulation no to
build a prototype to use that as a way
of trying to figure out what is it
you're really trying to do and that's
really if you can do that sort of thing
then you're really being agile are you
beginning to see clients build solution
abstractions modeling architectures now
because that was something that seemed
to disappear in the bigger agile in the
early days moving straight from user
stories to code where was the
architecture is that reappearing in
project it's very very slowly for a
reason I cannot explain architecture is
unpopular it's one of those necessary
things that nobody wants to talk about
and so architecture yes it is
reappearing and people of understanding
the need for it and so on but again
architecture is not doing itself any
favor with things like TOGAF nine and
only five people on the planet can
understand it properly so it's it's I'm
exaggerating here I hastened away but
wrapping it up in this arcane kind of
presentation is not doing it any favors
so for that reason it's it's unpopular
okay let's look at innovation you
mentioned that as one of the drivers if
you like for projects nowadays and why
we're developing software how do you
think innovation sit with that child I
can see how the proponents of our child
could argue it
sponsors and dynamic what are your
experiences
look we were actually arguing about this
earlier on today I'll present my version
which is no doubt the correct version of
this and then I'll argue the most
valuable innovations come early in the
project and the most valuable
innovations of those are the ones that
effect the problem space the hole now
I'll hasten to add here innovation is
not coming up with some new
technological gizmo with a
touch-sensitive glass screen or a new
iPad or anything else like that
innovation is fresh thinking thinking
differently about the problem area and
the most valuable innovations are the
ones where the whole problem is changed
because of some innovative fresh
thinking one example the springs to mind
simply because I'm doing at the moment
is first direct bank here in the UK
first rings brandy Bank was a brand new
bank about five years ago they started
by saying let's look at the whole
problem of banking and what is it that
people like and what is it people don't
like so rather than coming at it from a
traditional banking perspective they
said we want to look at banking from the
point of view of a customer okay which
is really quite an innovation when you
think about it cuz most banks look at
the banking from the point of view of
the bank and first erect came up with a
completely branch free paper free way of
banking it's all done on the internet or
over the telephone and importantly in
order to make this work because anybody
can implement that in order to make this
work they're fresh thinking or
innovative thinking was about the people
they hire
for the bank and they found them all in
the service industry if you've worked in
traditional banking you're not able to
work for first direct you have to come
from an airline or a hotel or something
to do with customer service and that's
what they were selling they said banking
is not about money it's about a customer
service and when you think about that's
perfectly correct but the concept all we
had earlier on with you said is well you
can't being agile doesn't mean you're
going to be innovative well I maintain
that if you are little a and child you
are developing and applying skills that
make it possible for you to say okay
this is where we are now so that other
people quickly quickly is that it's a
key word here so that other people can
understand what you're talking about
and then if you're really agile you say
we're not going any further we're going
to question all these things we're going
to question who's here are yes but
couldn't it be this I'm who are we going
to hire to do this why we really doing
it in the first place so now if you've
got to have some kind of starting point
because if people just brainstorm like
mad what ends up is they they have lots
of ideas that float around and that's
that but if you're really agile you can
get a starting point quickly something
that you can build on disagree with
replace and that's why I maintain that
ton little a agile makes you if you
really really have got it it will make
you more innovative well if you think
about big a agile and you know a time
box to sprint one iteration it doesn't
really leave you time for innovation
because you've got to you've committed
to building a piece of software by a
given date that's what you've got to do
that was the core of our disagreement
because you were talking about big a is
not innovative and I was talking about
little a is innovative but we were just
saying agile consequently we had to talk
it through let me try and mediate the
domestic dispute in front of me for the
listeners in case they're worried about
the consequence if you're on your
harmony I think this time boxing is an
interest
issue certainly I know from looking at
creativity and innovation that the
process of incubation mulling over ideas
thinking things through as possible in
this doesn't often fit well with the
need to be doing something and me seem
to do something
well innovation is not a rigid process
it's one of those bizarre things that we
don't know how long it takes to do it we
don't know how long ideas sit around
before they come to fruition the iPad in
one of the most successful consumer
devices in recent history took quite a
few years because it was kicked around
it changed it it morphed from one thing
to the other some of the ideas from the
iPad were put into the iPhone that was
developed first and then later the iPad
itself came along these things can't be
timed okay now in terms of value the
iPad is staggeringly valuable to Apple
it's also incidentally something that
nobody knew they wanted and this is part
of it just sort of a little diversion
here to let me say big our requirements
people don't know what they want nobody
listening to this I'm willing to bet
nobody listening to this broadcast knew
they wanted an iPad before they saw it
they be asked before they knew of its
existence do you need a tablet size
device to carry around and manipulate
purely with your fingers no keyboard the
answer would have been no but you're
talking about an invention well that's
an inventor as opposed to an innovator
I'm using it as an illustration of we
don't know what we want and so relying
upon traditional requirements gathering
techniques of sitting down and saying to
the customers sitting down saying to
users what do you want it doesn't work
similarly in Big Ang the roll
the product owner doesn't work because
one person from the business cannot
possibly know what is needed
he or she may know vaguely what they
think might be a solution but it's it's
it's proven to be flawed most clients
are moving away from having a single
product owner simply because this we
don't know what we want is it's coming
true making use of looking at the larger
larger picture within me within the
problem are you aware of any examples
about child projects that have led to
innovations within that business or more
widely that have led to innovations yes
an agile project has produced an
innovative outcome it's such an obvious
question I felt I should ask it
I think the silence coming the stuff at
a table says no we well I think we would
invite listeners to email or our social
media they're commenting on that by all
means I know that in the small you
couldn't see it but I can't I can't
isolate any beak thing now in the small
where where someone says oh could you
really do that I mean it's not
considered to be an innovation but it is
an innovation because it wouldn't have
happened otherwise something even more
convenient something that makes it
possible for somebody to do more work I
think the problem with innovation is we
always expect it to be a boatful from
the blue or from heaven or wherever
bolts come from you say about ok so
let's move on looking more broadly now
there's been a lot of association with
big a agile around so the use of some
tools and techniques
can ban user story cars and so on but if
you look more widely in software
engineering you're seeing focus on
governance rather than management focus
on the softer people skills that are
important focus on politics as well
nowadays understanding the role of
politics in software engineering do you
think these are important in agile
projects I think they're important in
all projects I'm not quite sure what
you're meaning by projects do you mean
government politics or internal I was
thinking more politics internal office
politics the the role of politics in the
target domain if you're seeking to
change a business there is inevitably
some power relationship which will be
which will enact be enacted as a
political action yes I think this is
leading business analysts in particular
to be better politicians because the
having something accepted is the most
difficult thing it's not hard to come up
with innovations it's selling the
innovation within the organization and
having people accept that is by far the
most difficult part of it but when I
just think about some of my clients
where they have said okay we want to be
agile and they're really trying to be
smaller agile they're really really
making an effort problem is that
sometimes the organizations are
structured in silos but the business
analysts have got to work across those
silos and in order to do that they've
got to be able to negotiate because the
different people in different silos have
got very very different purposes so once
again the business analysts have really
got to to get better and better at the
psychology and the app and the politics
since the and all these things that
naive business analysts don't realise
because they haven't been trained to do
that
they think that you know writing
requires down and building models and
being being big a edge
is what you should be doing and it's a
very different different um skill most
important business analyst skills are
not taught unfortunately politics are
very important the case comes to mind at
the people first section of the Royal
Borough of Kensington and Chelsea very
innovative approach to presenting what
is available to people and it's worth
while looking at this unfortunately the
link to people first is right at the
bottom of the roll bar a site and it's
hard to see without scrolling but if you
go there you see just what a fabulous
piece of work it is very innovative very
non-traditional local government but
they had to spot that the guys who made
it happen had to really know is a fact
they have to convince people across
different parts of the organisation that
it was okay to be as different as they
have been in their interface and you can
you can call that politics you can call
it selling even more of diplomacy
whatever you want to call it that was
what was required and it's very
necessary do you think the the reliance
about gel on communication and
collaboration more than writing things
down has increased the importance of
those softer skills that the analyst
needs
I think it's increased people's
awareness that they're necessary I think
they've always been very very important
but people haven't really been well
being prepared to admit it or being
aware of it I think I think that this
doesn't make people much more aware than
meaningful well it brings it up in the
open which is important because before
the business analyst was able to hide in
a cubicle and write things down and if
they weren't exactly M he or she could
always point at other people well now
with communication with verbal
communication
being so important it's very hard to
hide if you're having an open discussion
and I think that's a really good thing
to come out of one of them pretty good
things to come out of agile methods is
emphasis on well it means that some
education programs for business analysts
are more and more aware that we've got
to have not just a technical side and
you said that years ago they've the
socio-technical view and and that we
have to educate this assemblies in the
socio as well as the technical this mean
you're changing your training of
analysts to give them more thinking on
the feet skills because it seems to me
there is more immediate on your feet
thinking yes I mean in my business
analysis course I actually teach
presentation skills because part of the
politics diplomacy selling whatever you
want to call it is presenting ideas to
people and people are an audience is
much more likely to buy into an idea if
it is being competently presented if you
present understanding they're shuffling
mumbling and doing an appalling job then
the idea is thrown out along with the
with the presenter so all of these
skills of listening of talking of
presenting I even try and convince
people that drawing is an important
skill that if you can draw a little bit
better it's going to help you to get
your ideas across this is a very very
hard sell I know because Stan Rome for
example on on his website he focuses
very much on drawing and he's he's
really convinced a lot of people that
you can actually learn to draw well even
though you might not have an innate
talent for it and some of his lessons in
anybody in drawers just a matter of them
believing they can drawer and in order
to do and it doesn't have to be great
option I'm not talking about being the
break duck
being another david hockney or anything
it's just giving people the confidence I
think that they can they can do things
it's like that and what's that wonderful
Japanese sugar okay Pecha Kucha I to
cooker where you get somebody to make a
presentation that's really constrained
by time twenty slides each slide lasting
twenty seconds and they're automatically
advanced got three minutes and forty
seconds to get whatever it is across so
you can't be mumbling about bullet
points or so forth to could it be a
short chapter and it really is something
that people can do that and they don't
think they can and it's it's a wonderful
that's a Trulia not just going back to
to drawing sketching or if I can lead
into visualizing because if you could
present a diagram to somebody that
visualizes your idea it's much easier
for the other person to understand it
and they're much more likely to accept
it so we're moving from user stories to
use the storyboards if you like yes
that's any visual graphic presentation
is I think it is is important user
stories work very well also if they're
if they're intelligently used like
everything you know it's a really good
idea providing you can connect it to
everything else that's going but the
storyboard itself if we go back to
systemic thinking you get a much better
broader view of what's happening if
you've got the storyboard as opposed to
the the story card you're much more
likely to see the ramifications of
anything you're doing it's more
dimension it's it's more dimension and a
bit of visualization of it so looking to
the future what do you see is the the
big challenges for agile and
requirements over the next
years are the new trends that are gonna
pose challenges are we not there yet and
we still need to improve on what we're
doing in big a or little a agile I think
my biggest bug there and you probably
pick this up already it's business
analysts have to become better at
systems thinking so that they are
stronger and able to take new ideas and
not be driven by them and and
excessively he's been around for a hell
of a long time it's just that we haven't
really joined these things together and
I think we're starting to do it now I
look for example and Emma Langman gave a
talk at the be a conference last year
she gave that one of the keynotes and
she's focused on systems thinking him
Akili turned a lot of people's lights on
and and John none what's his name that's
it
John Seddon gave another talk about it
and and it's they came from that
discipline but the business analysts at
all
yes this is definitely a lot to do with
what we do and it would really help us
if we can do it better as it resides in
spring zero or sprint -1 or is the
systemic thinking happen through the
sprint cycles all the way through all
the ways although I'm going to say I
think the most valuable systemic
thinking happens at Sprint minus 1 or
minus 2 more somewhere back there
because the most valuable systemic
thinking the most valuable innovation
that all comes before you start to build
software we need a marathon before all
the sprints absolutely
something I see happening that I think
is a very very healthy thing is that the
religious aspect of agile is is fading
and people wanting to be agile but
they're adopting more and more of
traditional techniques the systemic
thinking is beginning to come
infiltrating into angel' innovation is
beginning to come into a circle wasn't
so I see this is being very healthy
because there are lots of good things in
agile but they're also good things that
are not traditionally part of a jar or
at least not not part of big a agile
would say so the wholesale adoption of
big a agile techniques is I see it as
being breaking down and people are
adopting a much more pragmatic approach
to developing a software future is that
how you see the future of agile
development in the next 5-10 years well
I hope so I mean I say I hope so because
you never know what's going to happen
and we've always had yet another
paradigm you know the red boxes Silver
Bullet syndrome I'm hoping and I and I'm
an optimist so I'm hoping that people
just start building on what we already
know and don't look for another miracle
which stops us getting better at what we
what we're doing I've seen slightly a
less emphasis on doing things quickly
now this is never gonna go away
the biggest problem is that we can
measure time we have calendars we have
clocks and so that's what we measure
what is harder the measure is
effectiveness and how valuable something
actually is how valuable a change
Cheers and it comes back to something
Lee I think opened our new edition of
our requirements book with if you're
going to build software it has to be
optimally invaluable to its owner and
it's this idea of value for the owning
organization which i think is slowly but
inevitably becoming part of software
development you know are we really
producing something which is not just a
quick fix for a current problem but are
we producing something which is
genuinely valuable is genuinely going to
make a difference within lead in the
business in order to be valuable it
probably has to be innovative it's very
hard to think of anything being valuable
if it is not an innovation if it is not
some significant change to what's there
at the moment so that's that's happening
you know seeing that happening more and
more I think seeing more and more of
more emphasis placed not on software but
on business analysis itself I'm just
using that as a a word to describe not
the role of the business analyst but the
role of actually analyzing the business
in finding out what the real problem is
and what are we going to do to make that
business more valuable and how to
actually make sure that the thread from
what we need to do to make it more
valuable is it's coherent to all the
people in the chain using whatever form
is appropriate to do it in that in that
time environment so if we take the
engineering part of software engineering
it's engineering the business
engineering the work being done
regardless of what the work is can be
commercial work and be scientific me
academic can be anything at all its
engineering the work and the end result
is usually a piece of software but we're
thinking more of the software is almost
an accidental byproduct of the
re-engineering of
the engineering of the other piece of
work is not reengineering it's
engineering yeah exciting times ahead
Susanne Robertson James Robertson thank
you very much for your time thank you I
know that was very interesting thank you
for having us thanks for listening to
s-see radio an educational program
brought to you by I Triple E software
magazine for more information about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se radio net to support
us you can advertise su Radio by
clicking the Digg reddit delicious or
slide buttons on the site or by talking
about us on Facebook Twitter or your own
blog if you have feedback specific to an
episode please use the commenting
feature on the site so that other
listeners can respond to your comments
as well this and all of the episodes of
se radio is licensed under the creative
commons two-point-five license please
see the website for details thanks again
for your support
[Music]
[Applause]